{
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "In this context of colonial India, the Government of India Act of 1935 recommended the establishment of:\n1. Council of India\n2. Bicameral legislature in provinces\n3. Federal form of government\n4. Central Public Service Commission\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 3 and 4 only",
          "(c) 2 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1 and 4 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "In medieval India, the term 'Amir-i-Chahalgani' referred to:",
        "options": [
          "(a) Foreign Invaders",
          "(b) Trusted Nobles",
          "(c) Women Spies",
          "(d) Agricultural labourers"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) Trusted Nobles"
      },
      {
        "question": "Dr. B.R Ambedkar was actively associated with which of the following?\n1. All India Harijan Sevak Sangh\n2. All India Scheduled Castes Federation\n3. Independent Labour Party\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 and 3 only",
          "(c) 1 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe Mountbatten Plan provided for:\n1. two Dominions and two Constituent Assemblies\n2. referendum in the North-West Frontier Province\n3. independence of princely states\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 3 only",
          "(b) 1 and 2 only",
          "(c) 3 only",
          "(d) 2 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 1 and 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to India, consider the following sites:\n1. Sammed Shikharji\n2. Shatrunjaya\n3. Thalaivetti Muniyappan\n4. Ashtapad\nWhich of the above are Jain pilgrimage sites?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "(c) 3 and 4 only",
          "(d) 2, 3 and 4 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 1, 2 and 4 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to 'Indian History', consider the following statements:\n1. The first Turkish invasion of India happened during the reign of Iltutmish.\n2. Mahmud of Ghazni is known for his raid on Somnath Temple during his invasion of India.\n3. In the Battle of Tarain, Prithviraj Chauhan defeated Ghurid forces and later captured the Tabarhinda region.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) 2 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the modern history of India, 'Damin-i-Koh' refers to:",
        "options": [
          "(a) duties imposed on the export of Indian handicrafts",
          "(b) revenue system imposed by the British authorities in North-east India",
          "(c) advances given by the English East India Company to merchants in Bengal",
          "(d) land exclusively demarcated for the Santhals to practise agriculture"
        ],
        "answer": "(d) land exclusively demarcated for the Santhals to practise agriculture"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the 'Anti-Compromise Conference', consider the following statements:\n1. It was convened by Muhammad Ali Jinnah at the Lahore session of the Muslim League in 1940.\n2. It was aimed at safeguarding the political rights of Muslims in India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) Both 1 and 2",
          "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who among the following established the 'Mahila Seva Mandal' and 'Native Female School' in Pune?",
        "options": [
          "(a) Aruna Asaf Ali",
          "(b) Jhalkari Bai",
          "(c) Savitribai Phule",
          "(d) Sarla Devi Chaudharani"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) Savitribai Phule"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following provisions under the Constitution of India ensures the 'Principle of Checks and Balances' in Indian Polity?\n1. Parliament is prohibited from discussing the judicial conduct of a Supreme Court judge\n2. Appointment of the High Court judges by the Executive Head of the State\n3. Judicial review exercised by the judiciary over legislative actions\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 2 and 3 only",
          "(c) 1 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The Supreme Court has clearly defined the basic structure of the Constitution in the Kesavananda Bharati case.\n2. The limited power of Parliament to amend the Constitution is a part of the basic structure of the Constitution.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) Both 1 and 2",
          "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to 'Money Bill', consider the following statements:\n1. It can be introduced only in the Lok Sabha and not in the Rajya Sabha.\n2. A joint sitting of both Houses of Parliament can be convened in case there is a deadlock.\n3. When it is presented to the President of India, it is obligatory for the President of India to give his/her assent.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 1 and 2 only",
          "(c) 3 only",
          "(d) 2 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct with respect to the Right to Freedom of Speech and Expression under Article 19 of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": [
          "(a) It is enforceable against private individuals and entities.",
          "(b) It is available to both citizens and foreigners except enemy aliens.",
          "(c) It cannot be restricted on any condition except those mentioned under Article 19.",
          "(d) It includes the right to receive and impart information through social media."
        ],
        "answer": "(b) It is available to both citizens and foreigners except enemy aliens."
      },
      {
        "question": "In India, the Directorate of Enforcement (ED) is a multi-dimensional organisation investigating economic offences under which of the following legislations?\n1. Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002\n2. Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999\n3. Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988\n4. Fugitive Economic Offenders Act, 2018\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 3 and 4 only",
          "(c) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 1, 2 and 4 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements with respect to the Memorandum of Procedure (MoP) for the appointment of the Chief Justice of India (CJI):\n1. The Ministry of Law and Justice seeks the recommendation of the outgoing CJI for the appointment of the next CJI.\n2. The next CJI must be appointed two months before the retirement of the outgoing CJI.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) Both 1 and 2",
          "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the 'Delimitation Commission', consider the following statements:\n1. The Minister of Home Affairs is the ex-officio member of the Delimitation Commission.\n2. It identifies seats to be reserved for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in Parliamentary and State Assembly elections.\n3. The Parliament can modify the orders of the Delimitation Commission only by a special majority.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) 2 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to Indian Polity, the 'Doctrine of Proportionality' is applied by the Judiciary to test:",
        "options": [
          "(a) the reasonable balance between laws and government actions",
          "(b) validity of a Constitutional Amendment Act",
          "(c) encroachment by the Central Government in the legislative jurisdiction of a State",
          "(d) validity of the Speaker's decision on the anti-defection laws"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) the reasonable balance between laws and government actions"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Unlike real GDP, nominal GDP does not account for any inflation in the economy.\n2. During inflationary periods, nominal GDP will be higher than real GDP.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) Both 1 and 2",
          "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the Indian economy, consider the following statements:\n1. A decline in Current Account Deficit would lead to an appreciation of Indian currency.\n2. An increase in the Reverse Repo Rate leads to an increase in the borrowing cost of loans.\n3. Increase in interest rate by the Federal Reserve of the United States of America would lead to an increase in capital inflow in the Indian economy.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 2 and 3 only",
          "(c) 1 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Purchase of government bonds from banks by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) most likely leads to inflation.\n2. The sale of dollars in the market by the RBI most likely leads to rupee appreciation.\n3. During inflation, the RBI is likely to increase the benchmark interest rates, including the repo rate.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 1 and 2 only",
          "(c) 2 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the 'G20 Summit', consider the following statements:\n1. Sherpa Track coordinates and prepares the agenda for the annual G20 summit meetings.\n2. Finance Track is the meeting of the Finance Ministers and the Central Bank Governors of the member countries.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) Both 1 and 2",
          "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements with reference to the Sovereign Green Bond:\n1. It is issued by the Reserve Bank of India.\n2. It is a part of the Government's overall market borrowing.\n3. It is a rupee-denominated paper that will not be available to foreign investors.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 and 2 only",
          "(b) 2 only",
          "(c) 1 and 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following items are exempted from the purview of the Goods and Services Tax in India?\n1. Sale of land\n2. All passenger air travel to the northeastern states\n3. Pre-packaged and labelled milk\n4. Distribution of electricity\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1, 2 and 3 only",
          "(b) 2 and 3 only",
          "(c) 1 and 4 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 1 and 4 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "A downward-sloping yield curve in an economy indicates:",
        "options": [
          "(a) economic slowdown in the future",
          "(b) imminent rise in interest rates",
          "(c) stable economy with no change in inflation",
          "(d) steep rupee depreciation"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) economic slowdown in the future"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to 'Open Offer', consider the following statements:\n1. It is a formal offer made by a company to the shareholders of a target company to sell their shares at a specified price.\n2. It can be initiated only if an acquirer holds the majority of the public shareholding in the target company.\n3. The share price offered in the open offer cannot be less than the market price of the shares at the time of acquisition.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 1 and 2 only",
          "(c) 3 only",
          "(d) 2 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "The drainage basin of the Brahmaputra River covers which of the following states?\n1. Assam\n2. Tripura\n3. Nagaland\n4. Sikkim\n5. Meghalaya\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "(b) 2, 3 and 5 only",
          "(c) 1, 3, 4 and 5 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 1, 3, 4 and 5 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following countries:\n1. Belarus\n2. Estonia\n3. Hungary\n4. Czech Republic\n5. Poland\nWhich of the above has borders with Ukraine?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "(b) 3, 4 and 5 only",
          "(c) 1, 3 and 5 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) 1, 3 and 5 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the Western Disturbances, consider the following statements:\n1. These are low-pressure storms that originate from subtropical high-pressure regions.\n2. Jet streams blowing south of the Himalayas bring in western disturbances in India.\n3. They are beneficial for the wheat and apple crops in the country.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 only",
          "(b) 1 and 2 only",
          "(c) 3 only",
          "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3"
      },
      {
        "question": "The perceived centre of the Sun's disk is in the same plane as the Equator when:",
        "options": [
          "(a) subsolar point hits the Tropic of Cancer around June 21",
          "(b) subsolar point hits the Tropic of Capricorn around December 21",
          "(c) the Earth's axis is not tilting toward or away from the sun.",
          "(d) the Earth is closest to the Sun"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) the Earth's axis is not tilting toward or away from the sun."
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following factors are responsible for the occurrence of debris avalanches and landslides in the Western Ghats?\n1. Steep slopes with vertical cliffs\n2. Tectonically active zone\n3. High temperature changes\n4. Heavy rainfall over a short period\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1, 3 and 4 only",
          "(b) 2 and 3 only",
          "(c) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "(a) 1, 3 and 4 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "The Government of India announces Minimum Support Price (MSP) for which of the following crops?\n1. Jowar\n2. Mustard seed\n3. Ginger\n4. Cotton\n5. Jute\n6. Sunflower seed\n7. Coffee\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1, 3 and 4 only",
          "(b) 1, 2, 4, 5 and 6 only",
          "(c) 2, 3, 5 and 7 only",
          "(d) 1, 2, 4, 5, 6 and 7 only"
        ],
        "answer": "(b) 1, 2, 4, 5 and 6 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Arrange the following Himalayan landforms in India from north to south with respect to their occurrence of formation:\n1. V-Shaped valleys\n2. Glacial lakes\n3. Estuaries\n4. Meanders\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1-2-4-3",
          "(b) 2-1-3-4",
          "(c) 2-4-1-3",
          "(d) 2-1-4-3"
        ],
        "answer": "(d) 2-1-4-3"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\nStatement 1: Mass movements are more active over weathered slopes than on un-weathered materials.\nStatement 2: Weathering is a necessary condition for mass movements.\nWhich one of the following is correct in respect of the above statements?",
        "options": [
          "(a) Both Statement 1 and Statement 2 are correct, and Statement 2 is the correct explanation for Statement 1",
          "(b) Both Statement 1 and Statement 2 are correct, but Statement 2 is not the correct explanation for Statement 1",
          "(c) Statement 1 is correct, but Statement 2 is not correct",
          "(d) Statement 1 is not correct, and Statement 2 is correct"
        ],
        "answer": "(c) Statement 1 is correct, but Statement 2 is not correct"
      },
      {
      "question": "Which is a landlocked sea?",
      "options": [
        "A) Arabian Sea",
        "B) Red Sea",
        "C) Baltic Sea",
        "D) Caspian Sea"
      ],
      "answer": "D) Caspian Sea"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the maximum strength of the Rajya Sabha?",
      "options": [
        "A) 250",
        "B) 545",
        "C) 238",
        "D) 552"
      ],
      "answer": "A) 250"

      },
      {
        "question": "Dr. B.R Ambedkar was actively associated with which of the following?\n\n1. All India Harijan Sevak Sangh\n2. All India Scheduled Castes Federation\n3. Independent Labour Party\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 2 and 3 only",
          "c) 1 and 3 only",
          "d) 1, 2 and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "b) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to ‘Indian History’, consider the following statements:\n\n1. The first Turkish invasion of India happened during the reign of Iltutmish.\n2. Mahmud of Ghazni is known for his raid on Somnath Temple during his invasion of India.\n3. In the Battle of Tarain, Prithviraj Chauhan defeated Ghurid forces and later captured the Tabarhinda region.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 2 only",
          "c) 2 and 3 only",
          "d) 1 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "c) 2 and 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Supreme Court has clearly defined the basic structure of the Constitution in the Kesavananda Bharati case.\n2. The limited power of Parliament to amend the Constitution is a part of the basic structure of the Constitution.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 2 only",
          "c) Both 1 and 2",
          "d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "c) Both 1 and 2"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to ‘Money Bill’, consider the following statements:\n\n1. It can be introduced only in the Lok Sabha and not in the Rajya Sabha.\n2. A joint sitting of both Houses of Parliament can be convened in case there is a deadlock.\n3. When it is presented to the President of India, it is obligatory for the President of India to give his/her assent.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 1 and 2 only",
          "c) 3 only",
          "d) 2 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "c) 3 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct with respect to the Right to Freedom of Speech and Expression under Article 19 of the Constitution of India?",
        "options": [
          "a) It is enforceable against private individuals and entities.",
          "b) It is available to both citizens and foreigners except enemy aliens.",
          "c) It cannot be restricted on any condition except those mentioned under Article 19.",
          "d) It includes the right to receive and impart information through social media."
        ],
        "answer": "a) It is enforceable against private individuals and entities."
      },
      {
        "question": "In India, the Directorate of Enforcement (ED) is a multi-dimensional organisation investigating economic offences under which of the following legislations?\n\n1. Prevention of Money Laundering Act, 2002\n2. Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999\n3. Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988\n4. Fugitive Economic Offenders Act, 2018\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 and 2 only",
          "b) 3 and 4 only",
          "c) 1, 2 and 4 only",
          "d) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "c) 1, 2 and 4 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements with respect to the Memorandum of Procedure (MoP) for the appointment of the Chief Justice of India (CJI):\n\n1. The Ministry of Law and Justice seeks the recommendation of the outgoing CJI for the appointment of the next CJI.\n2. The next CJI must be appointed two months before the retirement of the outgoing CJI.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 2 only",
          "c) Both 1 and 2",
          "d) Neither 1 nor 2"
        ],
        "answer": "a) 1 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to the 'Delimitation Commission’, consider the following statements:\n\n1. The Minister of Home Affairs is the ex-officio member of the Delimitation Commission.\n2. It identifies seats to be reserved for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in Parliamentary and State Assembly elections.\n3. The Parliament can modify the orders of the Delimitation Commission only by a special majority.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a) 1 only",
          "b) 2 only",
          "c) 2 and 3 only",
          "d) 1 and 3 only"
        ],
        "answer": "b) 2 only"
      },
      {
        "question": "With reference to Indian Polity, the ‘Doctrine of Proportionality’ is applied by the Judiciary to test:",
        "options": [
          "a) The reasonable balance between laws and government actions",
          "b) Validity of a Constitutional Amendment Act",
          "c) Encroachment by the Central Government in the legislative jurisdiction of a State",
          "d) Validity of the Speaker's decision on the anti-defection laws"
        ],
        "answer": "a) The reasonable balance between laws and government actions"
      },
      {
            "question": "Consider the following materials:\n\nAgricultural residues\nCorn grain\nWastewater treatment sludge\nWood mill waste\nWhich of the above can be used as feedstock for producing Sustainable Aviation Fuel?",
            "options": {
              "a": "1 and 2 only",
              "b": "3 and 4 only",
              "c": "1, 2, 3 and 4",
              "d": "1, 3 and 4 only"
            },
            "answer": "(c) 1, 2, 3 and 4"
          },
          {
            "question": "With reference to physical capital in the Indian economy, consider the following pairs:\n\nItems\tCategory\nFarmer's plough\tWorking capital\nComputer\tFixed capital\nYarn used by the weaver\tFixed capital\nPetrol\tWorking capital\nHow many of the above pairs are correctly matched?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Only one",
              "b": "Only two",
              "c": "Only three",
              "d": "All four"
            },
            "answer": "b Only two"
          },
          
          {
            "question": "Which one of the following words/phrases is most appropriately used to denote “an interoperable network of 3D virtual worlds that can be accessed simultaneously by millions of users, who can exert property rights over virtual items”?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Big data analytics",
              "b": "Cryptography",
              "c": "Metaverse",
              "d": "Virtual matrix"
            },
            "answer": "(c) Metaverse"
          },
          {
            "question": "With reference to the rule/rules imposed by the Reserve Bank of India while",
            "options": {
              "a": "Big data analytics",
              "b": "Cryptography",
              "c": "Metaverse",
              "d": "Virtual matrix"
            },
            "answer": "(d) Virtual matrix"
          },
          {
            "question": "Which of the following countries is expected to hold the largest share of global economic output by the year 2030?",
            "options": {
              "a": "India",
              "b": "China",
              "c": "United States",
              "d": "European Union"
            },
            "answer": "(b) China"
          },
          {
            "question": "Which of the following is a source of renewable energy?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Natural Gas",
              "b": "Wind",
              "c": "Nuclear",
              "d": "Coal"
            },
            "answer": "(b) Wind"
          },
          {
            "question": "What does the abbreviation 'AI' stand for in the field of technology?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Artificial Intelligence",
              "b": "Artificial Integration",
              "c": "Automated Intelligence",
              "d": "Algorithmic Interfacing"
            },
            "answer": "(a) Artificial Intelligence"
          },
          {
            "question": "In which of the following fields is the use of 'Blockchain' primarily applied?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Digital Currency",
              "b": "Healthcare",
              "c": "Retail",
              "d": "All of the above"
            },
            "answer": "(d) All of the above"
          },
          {
            "question": "Which of the following is NOT a programming language?",
            "options": {
              "a": "Python",
              "b": "Java",
              "c": "HTML",
              "d": "Swift"
            },
            "answer": "(c) HTML"
          },
         
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following best describes the term 'Giant Star' in Astronomy?",
              "options": {
                "a": "A star with more density and temperature than the Sun",
                "b": "A star formed after the death of a large star",
                "c": "A star with a mass 10 times or more than the mass of the Sun",
                "d": "A star with a lower density and temperature than a dwarf star (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following is a vasodilator synthesized in the human body?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Nitric oxide (Correct Answer)",
                "b": "Adenosine triphosphate",
                "c": "Carbon monoxide",
                "d": "Endothelin"
              },
              "answer": "a"
            },
            {
              "question": "Radar is used in which one of the following activities?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Weighing the ingredients while preparing a dish",
                "b": "Detecting the speed of a moving object (Correct Answer)",
                "c": "Measuring the depth of the ocean",
                "d": "Measuring the height of a building"
              },
              "answer": "b"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following is a fifth-generation fighter aircraft?",
              "options": {
                "a": "MiG-29",
                "b": "Dassault Rafale",
                "c": "F-16 Fighting Falcon",
                "d": "Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "In which one of the following is hydrogel used?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Growth of cells on culture medium (Correct Answer)",
                "b": "Remediation of contaminated groundwater",
                "c": "Wastewater treatment plants",
                "d": "Water conservation in agriculture"
              },
              "answer": "a"
            },
            {
              "question": "What is the final product that comes out of a hydrogen fuel cell electric vehicle?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Carbon dioxide",
                "b": "Hydrocarbon residue",
                "c": "Oxygen",
                "d": "Water (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following best describes the concept of 'Pumped-Storage Hydropower'?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Pumping water from lower to upper reservoir for irrigation",
                "b": "Storing rainwater in large underground tanks for reuse",
                "c": "Storing energy in the form of water for hydroelectric generation (Correct Answer)",
                "d": "Using tidal waves to pump water into coastal reservoirs"
              },
              "answer": "c"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following is likely to be found in a Membrane Bioreactor used for wastewater treatment?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Ultraviolet light",
                "b": "Ozonator",
                "c": "Electrical separator",
                "d": "Hollow fibre filter (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "What are Collateral Borrowing and Lending Obligations (CBLO)?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Long-term borrowings by scheduled commercial banks",
                "b": "Short-term borrowings by the government against gold",
                "c": "Money market instruments for borrowing/lending on a collateralized basis (Correct Answer)",
                "d": "Loans provided by NBFCs against property"
              },
              "answer": "c"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which of the following best defines a 'Greenfield Airport'?",
              "options": {
                "a": "A new airport built on undeveloped land (Correct Answer)",
                "b": "An existing airport upgraded to international standards",
                "c": "An airport that is eco-friendly and carbon-neutral",
                "d": "A military airbase converted to commercial use"
              },
              "answer": "a"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following statements about water vapour in the atmosphere is correct?",
              "options": {
                "a": "It absorbs long-wave radiation from the earth and raises the Earth's surface temperature (Correct Answer)",
                "b": "It absorbs long-wave radiation from the sun and cools the Earth",
                "c": "It reflects long-wave radiation from the Earth and decreases temperature",
                "d": "It radiates heat from the Earth's surface to the atmosphere"
              },
              "answer": "a"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following types of climate is characterized by mild winters and dry hot summers?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Mediterranean climate",
                "b": "Marine West Coast climate",
                "c": "Humid subtropical climate",
                "d": "Steppe climate (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "Which one of the following is caused by the Coriolis force?",
              "options": {
                "a": "Formation of tidal bores",
                "b": "Deflection of the ocean currents",
                "c": "Deflection of wind (Correct Answer)",
                "d": "Movement of monsoons"
              },
              "answer": "c"
            },
            {
              "question": "On 21st June, the Sun:",
              "options": {
                "a": "Does not set below the horizon at the Arctic Circle",
                "b": "Does not rise above the horizon at the Antarctic Circle",
                "c": "Shines vertically overhead on the Equator",
                "d": "Shines vertically overhead on the Tropic of Capricorn (Correct Answer)"
              },
              "answer": "d"
            },
            {
              "question": "Where is the world's largest tropical peatland located?",
              "options": {
                "a": "In the Congo Basin",
                "b": "In the Amazon Basin (Correct Answer)",
                "c": "In Indonesia",
                "d": "In Malaysia"
              },
              "answer": "b"
            },
          {
                    "question": "Which one of the following is a vasodilator synthesized in the human body?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Nitric oxide",
                      "b": "Adenosine triphosphate",
                      "c": "Carbon monoxide",
                      "d": "Endothelin"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Radar is used in which one of the following activities?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Weighing the ingredients while preparing a dish",
                      "b": "Detecting the speed of a moving object",
                      "c": "Measuring the depth of the ocean",
                      "d": "Measuring the height of a building"
                    },
                    "answer": "b"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following is a fifth-generation fighter aircraft?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "MiG-29",
                      "b": "Dassault Rafale",
                      "c": "F-16 Fighting Falcon",
                      "d": "Lockheed Martin F-22 Raptor"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "In which one of the following is hydrogel used?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Growth of cells on culture medium",
                      "b": "Remediation of contaminated groundwater",
                      "c": "Wastewater treatment plants",
                      "d": "Water conservation in agriculture"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What is the final product that comes out of a hydrogen fuel cell electric vehicle?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Carbon dioxide",
                      "b": "Hydrocarbon residue",
                      "c": "Oxygen",
                      "d": "Water"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following best describes the concept of 'Pumped-Storage Hydropower'?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Pumping water from lower to upper reservoir for irrigation",
                      "b": "Storing rainwater in large underground tanks for reuse",
                      "c": "Storing energy in the form of water for hydroelectric generation",
                      "d": "Using tidal waves to pump water into coastal reservoirs"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following is likely to be found in a Membrane Bioreactor used for wastewater treatment?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Ultraviolet light",
                      "b": "Ozonator",
                      "c": "Electrical separator",
                      "d": "Hollow fibre filter"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What are Collateral Borrowing and Lending Obligations (CBLO)?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Long-term borrowings by scheduled commercial banks",
                      "b": "Short-term borrowings by the government against gold",
                      "c": "Money market instruments for borrowing/lending on a collateralized basis",
                      "d": "Loans provided by NBFCs against property"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which of the following best defines a 'Greenfield Airport'?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "A new airport built on undeveloped land",
                      "b": "An existing airport upgraded to international standards",
                      "c": "An airport that is eco-friendly and carbon-neutral",
                      "d": "A military airbase converted to commercial use"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following statements about water vapour in the atmosphere is correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "It absorbs long-wave radiation from the earth and raises the Earth's surface temperature",
                      "b": "It absorbs long-wave radiation from the sun and cools the Earth",
                      "c": "It reflects long-wave radiation from the Earth and decreases temperature",
                      "d": "It radiates heat from the Earth's surface to the atmosphere"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following types of climate is characterized by mild winters and dry hot summers?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Mediterranean climate",
                      "b": "Marine West Coast climate",
                      "c": "Humid subtropical climate",
                      "d": "Steppe climate"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following is caused by the Coriolis force?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Formation of tidal bores",
                      "b": "Deflection of the ocean currents",
                      "c": "Deflection of wind",
                      "d": "Movement of monsoons"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "On 21st June, the Sun:",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Does not set below the horizon at the Arctic Circle",
                      "b": "Does not rise above the horizon at the Antarctic Circle",
                      "c": "Shines vertically overhead on the Equator",
                      "d": "Shines vertically overhead on the Tropic of Capricorn"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Where is the world's largest tropical peatland located?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "In the Congo Basin",
                      "b": "In the Amazon Basin",
                      "c": "In Indonesia",
                      "d": "In Malaysia"
                    },
                    "answer": "b"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "In India, which one of the following compiles information on industrial disputes, closures, retrenchments and lay-offs in factories employing workers?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Central Statistics Office",
                      "b": "Department for Promotion of Industry and Internal Trade",
                      "c": "Labour Bureau",
                      "d": "National Technical Manpower Information System"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "In India, under cyber insurance for individuals, which of the following benefits are generally covered?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Cost of restoration of computer system in case of malware disrupting access to one's computer",
                      "b": "Cost of a new computer system if the original is irreparable",
                      "c": "Cost of hiring a specialized consultant to minimize the loss in case of cyber extortion",
                      "d": "Cost of defense in the court of law if any third party files a suit"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "With reference to India, what is the advantage of generic drugs over branded drugs?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Generic drugs are manufactured in India whereas branded drugs are manufactured abroad",
                      "b": "Generic drugs are not tested on animals whereas branded drugs are tested on animals",
                      "c": "Generic drugs are cheaper and yet equally effective as branded drugs",
                      "d": "Generic drugs do not require any license whereas branded drugs require a license"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements: Statement-I: Carbon markets are likely to be one of the most widespread tools in the fight against climate change. Statement-II: Carbon markets transfer resources from the private sector to the State.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct and Statement-II is the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "b": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct but Statement-II is not the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "c": "Statement-I is correct but Statement-II is incorrect",
                      "d": "Statement-I is incorrect but Statement-II is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which of the following activities constitute real sector in the economy?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Farmers harvesting their crops",
                      "b": "Textile mills converting raw cotton into fabrics",
                      "c": "A commercial bank lending money to a trading company",
                      "d": "A corporate body issuing Rupee Denominated Bonds overseas"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the International Organization for Standardization (ISO): 1. ISO is an organ of the United Nations (UN). 2. ISO is a non-governmental organization. 3. ISO has a consultative status in the UN Economic and Social Council.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Only one statement is correct",
                      "b": "Only two statements are correct",
                      "c": "All three statements are correct",
                      "d": "None of the statements is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "b"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Kukis, frequently seen in news, are ethnic people living in which of the following states?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Manipur and Nagaland",
                      "b": "Meghalaya and Assam",
                      "c": "Tripura and Mizoram",
                      "d": "Arunachal Pradesh and Nagaland"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following is a reason why astronomical distances are measured in light-years?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Distance of stars and galaxies is huge and measuring it in kilometers becomes unmanageable",
                      "b": "Light-year is a time period suitable for space travel",
                      "c": "Light-year includes the speed of light so it is easy for astronomers",
                      "d": "Light-year is a unit for measuring brightness, which correlates with distance"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
               
       
            
              
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements in respect of the Laureus World Sports Award which was instituted in the year 2000: 1. American golfer Tiger Woods was the first winner of this award. 2. The award was received mostly by ‘Formula One’ players so far. 3. Roger Federer received this award the maximum number of times compared to others.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Only one statement is correct",
                      "b": "Only two statements are correct",
                      "c": "All three statements are correct",
                      "d": "None of the statements is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "b"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements: Statement-I: According to the United Nations’ World Water Development Report, 2022, India extracts more than a quarter of the world’s groundwater withdrawal each year. Statement-II: India needs to extract more than a quarter of the world’s groundwater each year to satisfy the drinking water and sanitation needs of almost 18% of world’s population living in India.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct and Statement-II is the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "b": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct but Statement-II is not the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "c": "Statement-I is correct but Statement-II is incorrect",
                      "d": "Statement-I is incorrect but Statement-II is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements regarding Chhattisgarh: 1. It is the only State in India to have 'laws enacted by the Panchayats' and not only rules or regulations. 2. The 'Scheduled Areas' in Chhattisgarh are spread over more than 50% of the State.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Only one statement is correct",
                      "b": "Both statements are correct",
                      "c": "Neither statement is correct",
                      "d": "None of the above"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements about G20: 1. G20 was established as a platform for Finance Ministers and Central Bank Governors to discuss international economic and financial issues. 2. It has since evolved into a forum for Heads of State or Government to address global economic challenges. 3. G20 members account for nearly two-thirds of the world population and around 75% of international trade.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Only one statement is correct",
                      "b": "Only two statements are correct",
                      "c": "All three statements are correct",
                      "d": "None of the statements is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements: Statement-I: The Government of India has declared the 'Hand Made Products' as Geographical Indications. Statement-II: Geographical Indications are defined under the TRIPS Agreement of the WTO.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct and Statement-II is the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "b": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct but Statement-II is not the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "c": "Statement-I is correct but Statement-II is incorrect",
                      "d": "Statement-I is incorrect but Statement-II is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which one of the following best defines the term 'Intended Nationally Determined Contributions' that is sometimes seen in the news?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "It is a plan presented by countries for reducing greenhouse gas emissions under the UNFCCC",
                      "b": "It is a financial assistance provided by developed countries to developing countries to mitigate climate change",
                      "c": "It is an international agreement among countries to share climate technologies",
                      "d": "It is a carbon trading mechanism under the Kyoto Protocol"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following pairs regarding G20 summit declarations and locations: 1. Bali Summit – Bali Common Framework on Debt Treatments 2. Rome Summit – Rome Declaration on Global Health 3. Osaka Summit – Osaka Blue Ocean Vision",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Only one pair is correctly matched",
                      "b": "Only two pairs are correctly matched",
                      "c": "All three pairs are correctly matched",
                      "d": "None of the pairs is correctly matched"
                    },
                    "answer": "c"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements: Statement-I: To provide for an effective legal framework for combating corruption in government agencies and public sector businesses in India, the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 was amended in the year 2018. Statement-II: The Amendment Act of 2018 introduced the offence of 'giving a bribe' as a direct offence and provided for punishment for abetment of offences by public servants.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct and Statement-II is the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "b": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are correct but Statement-II is not the correct explanation for Statement-I",
                      "c": "Statement-I is correct but Statement-II is incorrect",
                      "d": "Statement-I is incorrect but Statement-II is correct"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which civilisation is the oldest in the world?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Egyptian Civilization",
                      "b": "Mesopotamian Civilization",
                      "c": "Chinese Civilization",
                      "d": "Indus Valley Civilization"
                    },
                    "answer": "b"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Egypt is also called what?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Gift of Nile",
                      "b": "Gift of the World",
                      "c": "Gift of Sun",
                      "d": "Gift of Sphinx"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The potter’s wheel was first used in this civilisation.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Harappan Civilization",
                      "b": "Chinese Civilization",
                      "c": "Indus Valley Civilization",
                      "d": "Mesopotamian Civilization"
                    },
                    "answer": "d"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The first Olympic Games were held in?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "776 BC",
                      "b": "745 BC",
                      "c": "779 BC",
                      "d": "749 BC"
                    },
                    "answer": "a"
                  },
                  {
                   "question": "Which civilisation is the oldest in the world?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Egyptian Civilization",
                      "b": "Mesopotamian Civilization",
                      "c": "Chinese Civilization",
                      "d": "Indus Valley Civilization"
                    },
                    "answer": "Mesopotamian Civilization"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Egypt is also called what?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Gift of Nile",
                      "b": "Gift of the World",
                      "c": "Gift of Sun",
                      "d": "Gift of Sphinx"
                    },
                    "answer": "Gift of Nile"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The potter’s wheel was first used in this civilisation.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Harappan Civilization",
                      "b": "Chinese Civilization",
                      "c": "Indus Valley Civilization",
                      "d": "Mesopotamian Civilization"
                    },
                    "answer": "Mesopotamian Civilization"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The first Olympic Games were held in?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "776 BC",
                      "b": "745 BC",
                      "c": "779 BC",
                      "d": "749 BC"
                    },
                    "answer": "776 BC"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Who is known as the father of History?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Sophocles",
                      "b": "Homer",
                      "c": "Herodotus",
                      "d": "Aristophanes"
                    },
                    "answer": "Herodotus"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The ‘Age of Renaissance’ started in the century?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "16th Century",
                      "b": "15th Century",
                      "c": "14th Century",
                      "d": "19th Century"
                    },
                    "answer": "16th Century"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "When did the Reformation movement start?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1516",
                      "b": "1518",
                      "c": "1519",
                      "d": "1517"
                    },
                    "answer": "1517"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What was the Reformation movement?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "It was a revolt against King Henry VIII.",
                      "b": "It was the rise of the Church’s control over Rome.",
                      "c": "It was a revolt against the Pope and the letter of Indulgence.",
                      "d": "A movement to reform and rebirthing the art and literature of the 16th century."
                    },
                    "answer": "It was a revolt against the Pope and the letter of Indulgence."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The Industrial Revolution started in?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1760",
                      "b": "1764",
                      "c": "1761",
                      "d": "1762"
                    },
                    "answer": "1760"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Where did the Industrial Revolution first start?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Great Britain.",
                      "b": "France.",
                      "c": "Rome.",
                      "d": "America."
                    },
                    "answer": "Great Britain."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which year did Christopher Columbus discover America?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1490",
                      "b": "1492",
                      "c": "1491",
                      "d": "1494"
                    },
                    "answer": "1492"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What is the Magna Carta or the Great Charter of 1215?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "It was the Charter to increase the power of the king.",
                      "b": "Foundation of ending the tax system in England.",
                      "c": "The foundation of Rights and Liberties of English people.",
                      "d": "It was the setting stone for the king to rule over the Pope."
                    },
                    "answer": "The foundation of Rights and Liberties of English people."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The Reformation Movement was started by whom?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "King Henry VIII.",
                      "b": "Martin Luther.",
                      "c": "John Calvin.",
                      "d": "William Tyndale."
                    },
                    "answer": "Martin Luther."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The American war of Independence was fought from _____ to _____.",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1775 – 1784",
                      "b": "1777 – 1783",
                      "c": "1775 – 1783",
                      "d": "1770 – 1780"
                    },
                    "answer": "1775 – 1783"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What is the idea behind the Boston Tea Party?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Protest against the tax imposed on tea.",
                      "b": "Protest against the British rulers in the American colonies.",
                      "c": "Protest against the ending of the taxation imposed by the Britishers.",
                      "d": "Protest against the difficult conditions of tea plantation workers."
                    },
                    "answer": "Protest against the tax imposed on tea."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "When did Americans gain independence?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "4th July 1773",
                      "b": "4th July 1774",
                      "c": "4th July 1771",
                      "d": "4th July 1775"
                    },
                    "answer": "4th July 1775"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What is the duration of the French Revolution?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1788 – 1792",
                      "b": "1789 – 1799",
                      "c": "1789 – 1799",
                      "d": "1781 – 1790"
                    },
                    "answer": "1789 – 1799"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "What was the slogan for the French Revolution?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity.",
                      "b": "Liberty, Equality, Reform.",
                      "c": "Liberty, Revolution, Equality.",
                      "d": "Revolution, Reform, Fraternity."
                    },
                    "answer": "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity."
                  },
                  
               
                {
                  "question": "What was the slogan for the French Revolution?",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity.",
                    "b": "Liberty, Equality, Reform.",
                    "c": "Liberty, Revolution, Equality.",
                    "d": "Revolution, Reform, Fraternity."
                  },
                  "answer": "(a) Liberty, Equality, Fraternity."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Thirty Years’ war was fought from _____ to _____.",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "1618 – 1648",
                    "b": "1620 – 1640",
                    "c": "1629 – 1649",
                    "d": "1619 – 1949"
                  },
                  "answer": "(a) 1618 – 1648"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Whose reign was the king during the French Revolution?",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "Louis XVI",
                    "b": "Louis XV",
                    "c": "Napoleon",
                    "d": "Louis XIV"
                  },
                  "answer": "(a) Louis XVI"
                },
                {
                  "question": "Which treaty acknowledges the Independence of America?",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "Treaty of France",
                    "b": "Treaty of America",
                    "c": "Treaty of Paris",
                    "d": "Treaty of Versailles"
                  },
                  "answer": "(c) Treaty of Paris"
                },
                {
                  "question": "What was the purpose behind the Treaty of Westphalia?",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "The Treaty of Westphalia brought an end to the Eighty Years War between Spain and the Dutch.",
                    "b": "The Treaty of Westphalia brought an end to the Thirty Years’ War between the Dutch and the Germans.",
                    "c": "The Treaty of Westphalia brought an end to the Thirty Years’ War and The Eighty Years’ War.",
                    "d": "None of the above."
                  },
                  "answer": "(c) The Treaty of Westphalia brought an end to the Thirty Years’ War and The Eighty Years’ War."
                },
                {
                  "question": "The Soviet Union was made up of _____ republics.",
                  "options": {
                    "a": "20",
                    "b": "10",
                    "c": "17",
                    "d": "15"
                  },
                  "answer": "(d) 15"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\nThe Constitution of India gives the President the power to appoint the Chief Justice of India.\nThe President can remove a judge of the Supreme Court without any recommendation from the Parliament.\nThe Chief Justice of India is the ex-officio Chairman of the National Judicial Appointments Commission.\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1 only",
                      "b": "1 and 3 only",
                      "c": "2 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, and 3"
                    },
                    "answer": "a) 1 only"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which of the following statements about the 'Rajya Sabha' is correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Rajya Sabha is a directly elected body.",
                      "b": "Rajya Sabha is a permanent body, and its members are not subject to re-election.",
                      "c": "One-third of the members of Rajya Sabha retire every two years.",
                      "d": "The Rajya Sabha has more powers than the Lok Sabha in the case of money bills."
                    },
                    "answer": "c) One-third of the members of Rajya Sabha retire every two years."
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which of the following is/are considered as an exclusive power of the Lok Sabha?\n\nThe power to introduce money bills.\nThe power to dissolve the Lok Sabha.\nThe power to initiate the process of impeachment of the President.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1 only",
                      "b": "1 and 2 only",
                      "c": "1 and 3 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, and 3"
                    },
                    "answer": "b) 1 and 2 only"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The non-alignment movement (NAM) was started by the following leaders:\n\nJawaharlal Nehru (India)\nGamal Abdel Nasser (Egypt)\nKwame Nkrumah (Ghana)\nSukarno (Indonesia)\n\nWhich of the above statements are correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1, 2, and 3 only",
                      "b": "1, 2, and 4 only",
                      "c": "2, 3, and 4 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, 3, and 4"
                    },
                    "answer": "d) 1, 2, 3, and 4"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Which of the following is NOT included in the Directive Principles of State Policy?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Provision of adequate means of livelihood for all citizens",
                      "b": "Right to education",
                      "c": "Right to work",
                      "d": "Establishment of a uniform civil code"
                    },
                    "answer": "b) Right to education"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\nIndia is a member of the World Bank, IMF, and WTO.\nThe membership of the United Nations is limited to sovereign countries only.\nThe G-20 summit is attended only by the Finance Ministers of member countries.\n\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1 only",
                      "b": "1 and 2 only",
                      "c": "2 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, and 3"
                    },
                    "answer": "b) 1 and 2 only"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The Indian National Congress (INC) was founded in 1885 under the leadership of:",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "A.O. Hume",
                      "b": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
                      "c": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
                      "d": "Surendranath Banerjee"
                    },
                    "answer": "a) A.O. Hume"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "Consider the following about the Presidential Election in India:\n\nThe election is held through proportional representation by a single transferable vote.\nThe total value of the vote of each MP and MLA is the same.\nThe members of the Rajya Sabha are eligible to vote.\n\nWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1 and 2 only",
                      "b": "2 and 3 only",
                      "c": "1 and 3 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, and 3"
                    },
                    "answer": "c) 1 and 3 only"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The Government of India Act, 1935 provided for:\n\nThe establishment of a federal government in India.\nThe creation of a federal court.\nThe introduction of direct elections for the first time in India.\n\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "1 and 2 only",
                      "b": "1 and 3 only",
                      "c": "2 and 3 only",
                      "d": "1, 2, and 3"
                    },
                    "answer": "d) 1, 2, and 3"
                  },
                  {
                    "question": "The first battle of Panipat (1526) was fought between:",
                    "options": {
                      "a": "Babur and Ibrahim Lodi",
                      "b": "Babur and Rana Sanga",
                      "c": "Akbar and Hemu",
                      "d": "Akbar and Rana Pratap"
                    },
                    "answer": "a) Babur and Ibrahim Lodi"
                  },
                  
                    {
                      "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding the Monetary Policy Committee (MPC)?\n1. It decides the RBI's benchmark interest rates.\n2. It is a 12-member body including the Governor of RBI and is reconstituted every year.\n3. It functions under the chairmanship of the Union Finance Minister.",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 1 and 2 only",
                        "C. 3 only",
                        "D. 2 and 3 only"
                      ],
                      "answer": "A. 1 only"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "With reference to Manipuri Sankirtana, consider the following statements:\n1. It is a song and dance performance.\n2. Cymbals are the only musical instruments used in the performance.\n3. It is performed to narrate the life and deeds of Lord Krishna.",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1, 2 and 3",
                        "B. 1 and 3 only",
                        "C. 2 and 3 only",
                        "D. 1 only"
                      ],
                      "answer": "B. 1 and 3 only"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Who among the following was/were associated with the introduction of Ryotwari Settlement in India during the British rule?\n1. Lord Cornwallis\n2. Alexander Read\n3. Thomas Munro",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 1 and 3 only",
                        "C. 2 and 3 only",
                        "D. 1, 2 and 3"
                      ],
                      "answer": "C. 2 and 3 only"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "In the context of solving pollution problems, what is/are the advantage/advantages of bioremediation technique?\n1. It is a technique for cleaning up pollution by enhancing the same biodegradation process that occurs in nature.\n2. Any contaminant with heavy metals such as cadmium and lead can be readily and completely treated by bioremediation using microorganisms.\n3. Genetic engineering can be used to create microorganisms specifically designed for bioremediation.",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 2 and 3 only",
                        "C. 1 and 3 only",
                        "D. 1, 2 and 3"
                      ],
                      "answer": "C. 1 and 3 only"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "The Trade Disputes Act of 1929 provided for:",
                      "options": [
                        "A. the participation of workers in the management of industries",
                        "B. arbitrary powers to the management to quell industrial disputes",
                        "C. an intervention by the British Court in the event of a trade dispute",
                        "D. a system of tribunals and a ban on strikes"
                      ],
                      "answer": "D. a system of tribunals and a ban on strikes"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Kamban was a:",
                      "options": [
                        "A. Philosopher",
                        "B. Saint",
                        "C. Poet",
                        "D. Warrior"
                      ],
                      "answer": "C. Poet"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Karewas in Kashmir are known for:",
                      "options": [
                        "A. Saffron cultivation",
                        "B. Tea plantations",
                        "C. Rubber trees",
                        "D. Petroleum reserves"
                      ],
                      "answer": "A. Saffron cultivation"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "In India, Judicial Review implies:",
                      "options": [
                        "A. The power of the judiciary to review all the legislative enactments before they are signed by the President",
                        "B. The power of the judiciary to pronounce upon the constitutionality of laws and executive orders",
                        "C. The power of the judiciary to question the wisdom of laws enacted by the legislatures",
                        "D. The power of the judiciary to review its own judgments"
                      ],
                      "answer": "B. The power of the judiciary to pronounce upon the constitutionality of laws and executive orders"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "The object of the Butler Committee of 1927 was to:",
                      "options": [
                        "A. Define the jurisdiction of the Central and Provincial Governments",
                        "B. Define the powers of the Secretary of State for India",
                        "C. Impose censorship on national press",
                        "D. Improve the relationship between the Government of India and the Indian States"
                      ],
                      "answer": "D. Improve the relationship between the Government of India and the Indian States"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?",
                      "options": [
                        "A. Rights are claims of the State against the citizens",
                        "B. Rights are privileges which are incorporated in the Constitution of a State",
                        "C. Rights are claims of the citizens against the State",
                        "D. Rights are privileges of a few citizens against the many"
                      ],
                      "answer": "C. Rights are claims of the citizens against the State"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Which of the following best describes the term ‘import cover’, sometimes seen in the news in the context of India’s economy?",
                      "options": [
                        "A. The ratio of value of imports to the Gross Domestic Product of a country",
                        "B. The total value of imports of a country in a year",
                        "C. The ratio between the value of exports and that of imports",
                        "D. The number of months of imports that could be paid for by a country's international reserves"
                      ],
                      "answer": "D. The number of months of imports that could be paid for by a country's international reserves"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Regarding the taxation system of Krishna Deva, the ruler of Vijayanagar, consider the following statements:\n1. The tax rate on land was fixed depending on the quality of the land.\n2. Private owners of workshops paid an industry tax.",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 2 only",
                        "C. Both 1 and 2",
                        "D. Neither 1 nor 2"
                      ],
                      "answer": "C. Both 1 and 2"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "What is the purpose of the ‘Vidyanjali Yojana’ launched by the Government of India?",
                      "options": [
                        "A. To enable the famous foreign educational institutions to open their campuses in India",
                        "B. To increase the quality of education provided in government schools by taking help from the private sector and the community",
                        "C. To encourage voluntary monetary contributions from private individuals and organizations so as to improve the infrastructure facilities for primary and secondary schools",
                        "D. To provide midday meals to students in primary and secondary schools in backward areas"
                      ],
                      "answer": "B. To increase the quality of education provided in government schools by taking help from the private sector and the community"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "Consider the following pairs:\nTradition – State\n1. Chapchar Kut Festival – Mizoram\n2. Khongjom Parba ballad – Manipur\n3. Thang-Ta dance – Sikkim",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 1 and 2 only",
                        "C. 2 and 3 only",
                        "D. 1, 2 and 3"
                      ],
                      "answer": "B. 1 and 2 only"
                    },
                    {
                      "question": "With reference to the Parliament of India, consider the following statements:\n1. A private member's bill is a bill presented by a member of Parliament who is not elected but only nominated.\n2. Recently, a private member's bill has been passed in the Parliament of India for the first time in its history.",
                      "options": [
                        "A. 1 only",
                        "B. 2 only",
                        "C. Both 1 and 2",
                        "D. Neither 1 nor 2"
                      ],
                      "answer": "D. Neither 1 nor 2"
                    },
                    {
                        "question": "With reference to the Parliament of India, which of the following Parliamentary Committees scrutinizes and reports to the House whether the powers to make regulations, rules, sub-rules, etc. conferred by the Constitution or delegated by the Parliament are being properly exercised by the Executive within the scope of such delegation?",
                        "options": [
                          "A. Committee on Government Assurances",
                          "B. Committee on Subordinate Legislation",
                          "C. Rules Committee",
                          "D. Business Advisory Committee"
                        ],
                        "answer": "B. Committee on Subordinate Legislation"
                      },
                      {
                        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding Smart India Hackathon 2017?\n1. It is a centrally sponsored scheme for developing every city of our country into a smart city in a decade.\n2. It is an initiative to identify new digital technology innovations for solving the many problems faced by our country.\n3. It is a programme aimed at making all the financial transactions in our country completely digital in a decade.",
                        "options": [
                          "A. 1 and 3 only",
                          "B. 2 only",
                          "C. 2 and 3 only",
                          "D. 1, 2 and 3"
                        ],
                        "answer": "B. 2 only"
                      },
                      {
                        "question": "Which of the following gives 'Global Gender Gap Index' ranking to the countries of the world?",
                        "options": [
                          "A. World Economic Forum",
                          "B. United Nations Human Rights Council",
                          "C. United Nations Development Programme",
                          "D. World Health Organization"
                        ],
                        "answer": "A. World Economic Forum"
                      },
                      {
                        "question": "Consider the following in respect of the Indian Ocean Naval Symposium (IONS):\n1. Inaugural IONS was held in India in 2015.\n2. It is a voluntary initiative that seeks to increase maritime co-operation among navies of the littoral states of the Indian Ocean Region.",
                        "options": [
                          "A. 1 only",
                          "B. 2 only",
                          "C. Both 1 and 2",
                          "D. Neither 1 nor 2"
                        ],
                        "answer": "B. 2 only"
                      },
                      {
                        "question": "The term 'Digital Single Market Strategy' seen in the news refers to:",
                        "options": [
                          "A. ASEAN",
                          "B. BRICS",
                          "C. EU",
                          "D. G20"
                        ],
                        "answer": "C. EU"
                      }

                  
                  

                  

                
                ]
              }
              
               
          